Finding Aid for Finding Aid for School of Music (University of Michigan) Records, 1880-2010.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
School of Music (University of Michigan) records 1880-2010 1940-2010
University of Michigan. School of Music.
87322 Bimu C321 2
Music, theatre, and dance education unit of the University of Michigan and its predecessor organizations, the Ann Arbor School of Music and the University School of Music. Records of students and instructors, correspondence, topical files, and materials related to student and faculty performance groups. Archived versions of the School's websites provide additional documentation of academic programs, research, events, people, and policies.
33 linear feet
7 oversize volumes
2.13 GB
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group has been transferred in a number of accessions (donor no. 5155 ).
The School of Music records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The School of Music record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 9-25
Executive Officer Records -- Boxes 30-32
Music instruction at the University of Michigan was established by the Board of Regents on the recommendation of the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts in 1880, making it one of the first universities in the country to offer such instruction. Calvin B. Cady was the first instructor and commenced lessons in 1881, offering a theoretic and scientific course in music. He established the Ann Arbor School of Music (AASM) in 1881 to give private lessons to supplement his university income. In 1885 Cady became a professor; he resigned in 1888.
The University Musical Society was also founded in 1880. The purpose of the society was to stimulate musical appreciation in the university and community. Dr. Frieze, then acting university president, was instrumental in founding the society and university presidents served as presidents of the society well into the twentieth century. In 1881, the recently founded AASM became a division of the University Musical Society and degrees were conferred by the society. The school carried out instruction and concerts in cooperation with the society.
Albert A. Stanley took over the professorship of music and became director of the University Musical Society in 1888. The Ann Arbor and university communities helped the ailing school and society by holding a series of events and fundraisers in the early 1890s. The AASM was reorganized as the University School of Music (USM) in 1892; the University Musical Society continued to administer the school. After reorganization, $15,000 was raised by the School of Music Building Association to erect a building to house the school on Maynard Street. In 1896, the first commencement exercises were held at the school, with nine graduates participating. Two years later Frederick Stearns donated one of the largest collections of old and exotic instruments in the country to the USM.
The role of the USM expanded in 1905 when a resolution was adopted by the Board of Regents permitting students in the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts to elect USM courses in practical music and receive credit. In 1929, the school became a unit of the university, with degrees granted directly by the university, rather than the University Musical Society. The school continued to be administered by the University Musical Society board of directors, but matters of policy and principle were now subject to the approval of the University of Michigan Board of Regents. Title to real estate held by the Musical Society passed to the university which made an annual appropriation to assist in payment of expenses for the school. A master of music program was added to the curriculum in 1929.
In 1933, election of the Musical Society's board of directors became subject to regental approval. In 1940, the school became an autonomous unit of the university and separated completely from the University Musical Society. All instructors and professors were put on salary and no longer received commissions from private lessons. The University Musical Society retained the privilege of giving concerts in university buildings and was allowed space for their administrative functions in the Burton Memorial Tower.
In 1922, Earl V. Moore became the director of the Musical Society and school. In 1946, he became the first dean of the University of Michigan School of Music, serving in this capacity until 1960. In 1940, enrollment in the school stood at 303 students with 40 faculty members. Seventy-two concerts were given in 1940. In 1945, the curriculum was expanded to include a doctor of philosophy degree in musicology and music education and a doctor of education degree in music education. In the 1950s, the study of music history was enhanced by the acquisition of the famous Stellfeld Collection of music, including manuscripts of 17th and 18th century composers. In 1953, a doctor of musical arts degree was created providing a professional degree in composition and performance. By 1960 enrollment had increased to 500 students with 50 graduate students and a teaching staff of 59. In 1960, James Wallace became dean and served until 1970, when he was replaced by Allen Britton.
The growing numbers of students created space problems for the school. In 1964, a new building designed by architect Eero Saarinen was dedicated on north campus. Prior to moving into the new building, the school had been housed in 13 buildings scattered throughout campus. In 1975, the name of the building was changed to the Earl V. Moore Building in honor of the distinguished dean. The Margaret Dow Towsley Center, an addition to the Moore Building, was dedicated in 1985. The Center contains a Vocal Arts Center, Organ Recital Studio, and Stearns Collection exhibit rooms and was the result of a capital campaign begun in 1980 to raise funds for the school.
In 1971, a doctor of philosophy in theory was added to the curriculum and a bachelor of musical arts in 1973. By the 1972-1973 school year, the School of Music was composed of 106 faculty members and 861 students, including 274 graduate students. The school expanded in the 1970s with the addition of a dance department. Programs in composition and performance were enhanced by the building of one of the five best electronic music studios in the western hemisphere. By the end of the decade the diversity of the school could be seen in its many departments: Music History/Musicology, Conducting, Theory, String, Organ, Dance, Piano, Music Education, Composition, Voice, and Wind and Percussion Instruments. In 1980, Paul Boylan became dean of the school.
The first official university band was organized in 1935. It performed at athletic events and gave occasional concerts. By the 1960s there were six university bands (Symphony, Concert, Marching, Symphonic Wind Ensemble, Varsity, and Jazz). The bands are under the direction of School of Music faculty. The Marching Band has gained fame in recognition of its quality and precision in performance which have been highlighted during performances on televised football games. In 1972 the William D. Revelli Band Hall was dedicated, named in honor of the distinguished university band director.
Vocal music has also been a priority of the school; the first choir was established in 1942 and the chamber choir in 1965. The Men's and Women's Glee Clubs, the Arts Chorale, and Michigan Singers have also provided a training ground for young musicians and vocalists at the university.
The records of the School of Music and its predecessor organizations, the Ann Arbor School of Music and the University School of Music document music education in Ann Arbor and the University of Michigan and student and faculty musical production beginning in 1885. The records include a Student ledgers listing names, tuition, and instructors; correspondence and clippings, 1924-1953, concerning University Band, including correspondence of William D. Revelli; files relating to musical programs, particularly the Michigan Singers' Spring Tour, the Union Opera, and Musket productions; minutes of the executive committee and minutes of the faculty; and publications. The School of Music records are composed of two series, School of Music Topical Files and Dean's Correspondence, together totaling 7.5 linear feet and 7 outsized volumes.
Subjects:
Michigan Union Opera.; Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Musicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Band.; University of Michigan--Choral organizations.; University of Michigan. School of Music.; University School of Music.; Ann Arbor School of Music.; University of Michigan--Bands.; University of Michigan--Orchestras.
Contributors:
Revelli, William D. (William Donald), 1902-1994.
Genre/Form:
College publications.
- Topical Files 1891-1999
  The Topical File series is comprised of two separate alphabetical files. The first, received in the early accessions of School of Music records, covers the years 1891-1982. The second, received in 2005, covers the years 1962-1999.
  - 1891-1982
    The majority of the files in the School of Music Topical Files, 1891-1982 subseries (5.0 linear feet) document the School of Music after 1940, when it became an autonomous unit of the University of Michigan. The majority of these files are comprised of the minutes of faculty meetings (1942-1952, 1957-1983), and executive committee meetings (1946-1951, 1960-1987). These minutes and the Faculty Communications files (1957-1979) along with the Regents Communications files (1926-1929, 1953-1981) are good sources for documenting school activities and development of administration policies.
    The early years of the School of Music are sparingly documented. The Reports, 1880 file contains (copies of) the original reports drafted to the Board of Regents requesting a professorship in music and the regents response to the request. The materials in the Building Association file document the issuing of bonds to build the Maynard Street structure in 1893. The Student Ledgers, an incomplete run from 1881 to 1940, list student names, tuition, and instructors.
    Other documentation pertains to student performance groups, School of Music buildings, and efforts to raise funds for the school. The documentation of student groups mostly consists of correspondence for tour and performance arrangements and does not address the creative process. Much of the material relates to the University Band from 1924 to 1953, including correspondence and clippings. There is Michigan Singers correspondence from 1953 to 1962, and Union Opera news releases, correspondence, and clippings from 1951 to 1956. In the 1956/57 school year the Union Opera became coeducational and changed its name to Musket. There are Musket news releases, minutes, and correspondence from 1956 to 1962. The Men's and Women's Glee Clubs files consist of correspondence relating to touring and performances. The International Center files (1956-1961) document spring tours given around Michigan by international students to increase appreciation for diverse cultures. Photographs of student performance groups are found in the Student Touring Organizations Scrapbook which dates from the 1950s.
    There are several files related to the funding and building of School of Music buildings. The conception and planning process for the Earl V. Moore Building is documented in the New Building files, which include news clippings and a drawing of the old school of music building on Maynard Street before it was razed in 1965.
    The capital campaign files document a three-year campaign to expand facilities, to develop a sound recording laboratory, to build an institute for advanced studies in music, and to establish a residential string quartet. The campaign was part of a university-wide fund-raising drive begun in 1980 and active through 1983. The School of Music tied the campaign into their centennial celebration entitled "For Century II." The Development Committee minutes, and Development of Public Relations files document additional fund-raising efforts of the school.
    - Ad-hoc Committee on Space Needs and Room Utilization 1964-1970 (Box 1)
    - Arts Chorale 1953-1954 (Box 1)
    - Band, University of Michigan 1924-1953
      - A-Z, 24 folders (Box 1)
      - American Bandmasters Association (Box 1)
      - Assistance Fund (Box 1)
      - Buick (Box 1)
      - Bursley, Dean J. A. (Box 1)
      - Cavender, George, R. (Box 1)
      - Falcone, Nicholas D. (Box 1)
      - Harris Hall (Box 1)
      - Lee, Jack K. (Box 1)
      - Revelli, William D. (Box 1)
      - Rose Bowl Trip January, 1948 (Box 1)
    - Building Association 1891-1926 (Box 1)
    - Capital Campaign
      - Activities 1982-1983 (Box 1)
      - Case Statement (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 1980-1981 (Box 1)
      - Donors 1982-1983 (Box 1)
      - Draft 1982 (Box 1)
      - Executive Committee 1982 (Box 1)
      - Minutes 1981, 1983 (Box 1)
      - Organization 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - Capital Outlay and Planning 1973-1979 (Box 1)
    - Development Committee (minutes)
      - 1971-1981, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Development of Public Relations 1970-1981 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee (minutes)
      - 1940-1941
        - Tenure Cases
          - Hanns Pick 1941 (Box 2)
          - Wassily Besekirsky & Hanns Pick 1941-1942 (Box 2)
      - 1941-1951, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - 1960-1981, 13 folders (Box 2)
      - 1982-1987, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - Faculty Communications
      - 1957-1979, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Faculty Evaluations 1973
    - Faculty Meetings (minutes)
      - 1942-1983, 18 folders (Box 3)
    - International Center (Box 4)
      - Between Semester Tour
        - 1956-1958, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Spring Tour
        - 1957-1961, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Men's Glee Club 1953-1954 (Box 4)
    - Men's and Women's Glee Club Concert April, 1950 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Singers
      - General
        - 1953-1962, 8 folders (Box 4)
      - Spring Tours
        - 1954-1957, 4 folders (Box 4)
        - 1960-1962, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Student Manager's Correspondence 1953-1954 (Box 4)
    - MUSKET
      - General 1961-1962 (Box 4)
      - News Releases
        - 1956-1962, 5 folders (Box 4)
      - Powder and Horn Society (Box 4)
      - Union Coed Show 1956-1957 (Box 4)
    - National Association of Schools of Music (NASM)
      - Self-Survey 1960 (Box 4)
      - Self-Survey 1970, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - New School of Music Building on North Campus
      - General 1958-1970 (Box 5)
      - Clippings 1960-1965 (Box 5)
      - Dedication Correspondence 1964 (Box 5)
      - Preparation for Plans for School of Music Building, Documentation 1950-1956 (Box 5)
    - Outline of Plan for the Organization and Administration of a Conservatory of Music in Connection with the University of Michigan circa 1890 (includes minutes and drawings) (Box 5)
    - Planning 1980-1989 (Box 5)
    - "Planning Activities 1968 1975" Report to Academic Affairs Advisory Committee, 1963 (Box 5)
    - Proposals for Music Centers 1987 (Box 5)
    - Regents Communications
      - 1926-1929 (Box 5)
      - 1953-1981, 10 folders (Box 5)
    - Report on the Work of the Professor of Music and Instruction in Music 1880 (Box 5)
    - Scholarship Concerns Committee 1972-1975 (Box 5)
    - Stellfeld Collection 1954-1956 (Box 5)
    - Student Touring Organizations, Scrapbook (Box 5)
      (includes black and white, positive photographic prints, ca. mid 1950s)
    - Symphony Orchestra 1954-1955 (Box 5)
    - Theater and Drama Department Transfer 1983-1990 (Box 5)
    - Union Opera
      - General
        - 1951-1956, 5 folders (Box 5)
      - News Releases
        - 1953-1956, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Study Committee 1954-1955 (Box 5)
    - University Choirs
      - 1959-1961, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - University Orchestra 1958-1961 (Box 5)
    - Women's Glee Club
      - 1945-1954 (Box 5)
      - Award Fund (Box 5)
    - William P. Woodworth Cello Collection 1960-1961 (Box 5)
  - circa 1962-1999
    Topical Files ca. 1962-1999 include any number of topics ranging from budget issues to buildings, events, the centers and collections housed by the School of Music, clubs, projects, and University initiatives.
    - Afro-American Music Collection
      - Jesseye, Eva 2 folders (Box 25)
      - Patterson, Willis (Box 25)
    - All-State Program
      - Santa, Don (Box 25)
    - Assistant Dean for Academic Affairs
      - Coleman, Earl July 1988-November 1992 (Box 25)
    - BFA Review Committee (Box 25)
    - Bolcom's McTeague (Box 25)
    - Budget Changes
      - 1997-1998 (Box 25)
      - 1998-1999 (Box 25)
    - Central Conservatory of Beijing (Box 25)
    - Center for Continuing Education of Women (Box 25)
    - Center for Early Music (Box 25)
    - Chair's Annual Faculty Assessment
      - 1996 (Box 25)
      - 1997 (Box 25)
      - 1998 (Box 25)
    - Chamber Music Ann Arbor (Box 25)
    - Committee on the Economic Status of the Faculty 9/1988 (Box 25)
    - Committee on International Studies 1989-1993 (Box 25)
    - Computer Aural Skills Training (Box 25)
    - Conflict of Interest (Box 25)
    - Corning Collection (Box 25)
    - Dance Department
      - 1973-1989 (Box 25)
      - Review 1983-1984 (Box 25)
      - Sparling, Robert (Box 25)
    - Dean for Undergraduate Studies (Box 25)
    - Detroit Public Schools 1992-1993 (Box 25)
    - Detroit Symphony Orchestra 1962-1987 (Box 26)
    - Development Director Applications (Box 26)
    - Doctoral Programs in Music (Box 26)
    - Early Music Academy (Box 26)
    - Early Music Program (Box 26)
    - Election, Ombudsman Information (Box 26)
    - Electronics, Service & Studio (Box 26)
    - Ensembles (Box 26)
    - Eugene Power and Sadye Scholarship 2 Folders (Box 26)
    - Eugene and Sadye Power, Summer Fellowship (Box 26)
    - Evaluation and Planning Project 1977 (Box 26)
    - Evian Festival
      - 1981 (Box 26)
      - 1986 (Box 26)
    - Faculty Council on Graduate Studies (Box 26)
    - Faculty Grievance Procedures (Box 26)
    - Faculty Meetings Agenda and Minutes
      - 1990-1998 (Box 26)
      - 1979-1990 (Box 26)
    - Faculty Meetings (Box 27)
      - General Information (Box 27)
    - Frieze Memorial Organ (Box 27)
    - Future of the University Retreat (Box 27)
    - Ghana Project
      - Crawford, David E. (Box 27)
    - Guang Xi Art College, China (Box 27)
    - Harassment Policies (Box 27)
    - Hill Auditorium Campaign (Box 27)
    - Hill Auditorium 2 Folders (Box 27)
    - Ho, Edward (Box 27)
    - Information and Library Sciences (Box 27)
    - In-State Recruitment Program 1988 (Box 27)
    - Introductory Composition Requirement (Box 27)
    - International Viola Congress (Box 27)
    - International Council of Fine Arts Deans 1981-1991 (Box 27)
    - Istomin, Eugene 1991-1992 (Box 27)
    - ITIC Building (Box 27)
    - Jazz Program
      - Sarath, Edward (Box 27)
    - Keyboard Studies (Box 27)
    - Lahti, Christine (May 1992 Commencement Speaker) (Box 27)
    - Lesbian and Gay Men Office (Box 27)
    - LSA "Blue Ribbon Commission" Report 1986 (Box 27)
    - Mannion, Elizabeth (Box 27)
    - Marceau, Marcel (Box 27)
    - Marching Band
      - Lewis, Gary Joe (Box 27)
    - Men's Glee Club (Box 27)
    - Metropolitan University, Mexico City (Box 28)
    - Michigan Society of Fellows 1976-1991 (Box 28)
    - Midwestern Conference (Box 28)
    - MIME Center (Box 28)
    - Moody, Sr., Charles D. (Box 28)
    - Mozart's Piano Concertos Symposium November 1989 (Box 28)
    - Music Education Dept.
      - Froseth, Jo 1988-1993 (Box 28)
    - Music Pedagogy (Box 28)
    - Musical Arts Degree Program Committee (Box 28)
    - North Campus
      - Landscape Study February 1995 (Box 28)
      - Commons Development (Box 28)
      - Deans (Box 28)
    - New World String Quartet February 1991 (Box 28)
    - Nismann, Barbara A. (Box 28)
    - Newport Classic LTD Recording Agreement (Box 28)
    - Office of the Vice-President for Research
      - Wilson, L.W. (Box 28)
    - Office of the President
      - Duderstadt, J.J.
        - 1991-1996 (Box 28)
        - Inaugural Group (Box 28)
      - Advisory Committee (Box 28)
    - President's Report (Box 29)
    - Policies and Procedures (Box 29)
    - Patterson, Willis (Box 29)
    - Power Center Renovation (Box 29)
    - Provost Advisory Committee on Excellence (PACE) (Box 29)
    - Retirement Furloughs (Box 29)
    - Regental Correspondence (Box 29)
    - Rorke, Margaret Winter 1989 (Box 29)
    - Rake's Progress 1982-1985 (Box 29)
    - Rackham
      - D'Arms, John (Dean) 1985-1989 (Box 29)
    - Rehearsal Hall Renovations (Box 29)
    - Richards, Lloyd January 1994 (Box 29)
    - Seven Springs Group
      - 1990 (Box 29)
      - 1993 (Box 29)
      - 1994 (Box 29)
      - 1996 (Box 29)
    - Secretary IV Applications (Box 29)
    - Scholarly Exchange Programs January 1989 (Box 29)
    - School of Education
      - Miskel, Cecil (Dean) 1988 (Box 29)
    - School of Music Research Council (Box 29)
    - School of Music Elections (Box 29)
    - School of Art and Design Deanship Search (Box 29)
    - Symposium on Performance/Athletics of African Americans 1993 (Box 29)
    - Salsburg Festival Summer Academy August 1989 (Box 29)
    - Shepherd Wing (Revelli Hall Addition, 1998) (Box 29)
    - The Michigan Mandate: Linking Academic Excellence and Social Diversity March 1990 (Box 30)
    - Task Force on Recruitment 1983 (Box 30)
    - University Productions Personnel
      - 1989-1994 (Box 30)
      - Kraus, Jeffrey (Box 30)
    - Undergraduate Curriculum Review Committee 1989-1990 (Box 30)
    - Undergraduate Studies
      - Budget (Box 30)
    - University Musical Center 1979-1986 (Box 30)
    - Vocal Arts Center and Organ Studio (Box 30)
    - Workforce Analysis of Female Instructional Staff 1990 (Box 30)
    - Xian Conservatory of Music (Box 30)
- Student Ledgers 1885-1940
  The Student ledgers consist of an annual listing of student name, tuition, and instructors for the yeas 1885-1940 when the school operated as the Ann Arbor School of Music and University School of Music.
  - 1885-1889 (Volume 1)
  - 1893/94-1904 (Volume 2)
  - 1902/03-1906/07 (Volume 3)
  - 1906/07-1914/15 (Volume 4)
  - 1914/15-1925/26 (Volume 5)
  - 1925/26-1935/36 (Volume 6)
  - 1935/36-1939/40 (Volume 7)
- Dean's Files
  - Paul Boylan
    - Correspondence
      The Dean's Correspondence series, 1988-1993, (2.5 linear feet) is comprised of one folder of correspondence with professor John McCollum, and a chronological file of Dean Paul Boylan's outgoing correspondence from January 1988 through June 1993. Correspondence relates to both internal and external matters including information on faculty appointments, music education programs, and curriculum.
      - Dean Paul Boylan Correspondence with John McCollum 1978-1982 (Box 6)
      - Chronological File
        - January-December, 1988, 12 folders (Box 6)
        - January-December, 1989, 12 folders (Box 6)
      - January-December, 1990, 12 folders (Box 7)
      - January-December, 1991, 12 folders
        - January-December, 1992, 12 folders (Box 8)
        - January-June, 1993, 6 folders (Box 8)
- Faculty Records
  Faculty Records is broken into five subseries: Faculty Files (10 linear feet), Deceased Faculty Files (2 linear feet), Promotion Files (4.5 linear feet), Sabbatical Requests(.5 linear feet), and Faculty Activity Reports (1 linear feet)
  - Faculty File